The purpose of philosophy is not to help men find the meaning of life,
but to prove to them that there isn't any.
These are the words of Dr. Simon Pritchett, a professor of philosophy,
and they capture the spirit of the intellectuals who claim to be above mere commerce,
while living off the products of the very industries they despise.
Previously, at the Reardon Party, Francisco dropped his mask and delivered the money speech.
So, you think that money is the root of all evil? Have you ever asked what is the root of money?
He argued that money is a tool of virtue, not evil, that it represents trade, not exploitation.
The intellectuals were stunned. Riardon was intrigued.
Welcome back to Atlas Shrugged. In our last episode, we witnessed Francisco's money speech,
a philosophical defense of wealth and free exchange.
Today, we explore the conflict between those who value commerce and production,
and those who claim to represent higher non-commercial values.
We'll meet Dr. Robert Stadler, a brilliant physicist who has sacrificed his integrity for
political survival and witness the state science institute's attack on Reardon Metal.
The title, the non-commercial refers to those who claim to be above mere commerce,
intellectuals, scientists, and artists who profess contempt for business while
depending on its products for their existence.
The chapter opens with the State Science Institute releasing a statement attacking
Reardon Medal as unsafe.
The statement contains no actual evidence against the Medal,
no data, no scientific argument, no concrete objection,
just vague insinuations and appeals to authority,
designed to create doubt in the public mind and threaten the Rio Norte line project.
This is how the non-commercial world operates,
not through evidence and reason,
but through authority and innuendo.
The Institute cannot prove Reardon Medal is dangerous,
so it simply implies that it might be,
and let's fear do the rest.
Dagnie goes to confront Dr. Robert Stadler, the brilliant physicist who heads the State Science Institute.
She hopes that this man, once considered one of the greatest scientific minds of the age,
will speak the truth about Reardon Metal. What she discovers is devastating.
Stadler admits privately that Reardon Metal is a remarkable thing, but he refuses to say so publicly.
Stadler represents the tragedy of genius without integrity.
Once one of the greatest physicists in the world, he has allowed himself to become
dependent on government funding and political favor. He has traded his independence for security,
and now he must serve political masters rather than truth. Here's the key insight.
Stadler considers practical matters beneath him. He thinks he can pursue pure science while
ignoring the political uses to which it is put. But by accepting government money,
he has made himself an instrument of the looters. His contempt for the practical has destroyed his
ability to be impractical.
The chapter explores a deeper philosophical conflict, the contempt that intellectuals have for commerce and production.
Scientists like Stadler consider business vulgar. They claim to pursue truth for its own sake, untainted by material concerns.
Artists like Balfe Ubank believe the commercial success is proof of artistic failure.
The cultural establishment agrees money is dirty, profit is exploitation, and anyone who creates wealth is morally suspect.
But here's what they don't acknowledge. Every scientist, every artist, every intellectual depends on the products of commerce for their existence.
The food they eat, the buildings they work in, the tools they use. All created by the businessmen they despise.
The non-commercial class is parasitic on the commercial. They cannot exist without producers, yet they claim moral superiority over those who feed them.
Let's recap what we learned today.
The State Science Institute attacks
Reardon Medal with vague insinuations rather than evidence,
revealing how the non-commercial world operates
through authority rather than reason.
Dr. Robert Stadler, once a brilliant scientist,
has sacrificed his integrity for government funding.
He knows Reardon Medal is safe, but refuses to say so publicly.
The intellectual establishments contempt for commerce
is parasitic.
They depend on producers while despising them.
And the attack on Reardon Medal is part of a larger pattern.
The looters cannot compete through merit,
so they use institutions like the State Science Institute
to destroy what they cannot create.
In the next episode, we'll see who truly exploits
whom is the equalization of opportunity bill passes,
stripping Reardon of his or mines.
The looters tighten their grip, but the producers
prepare to fight back.
See you in the next one.