The man who speaks to you of sacrifice speaks of slaves and masters and intends to be the master.
The equalization of opportunity bill has passed.
Hank Reardon must sell his or mines property he built through decades of work,
to men who could never dig a single chunk of ore from the earth.
The looters call this fairness.
Rand calls it exploitation.
Previously, the State Science Institute published a report attacking Reardon medal,
not because it's dangerous, but because Reardon succeeded without their permission.
Even Dr. Robert Stadler, a brilliant physicist who knows the truth, signed off on the false report.
Science has been corrupted by politics. Welcome back to Atlas Shrugged.
In our last episode, we saw how the intellectual establishment attacks producers through
institutions like the State Science Institute. Today, the assault becomes direct.
The equalization of opportunity bill passes, forcing Reardon to sell his or mines.
We'll see who truly exploits whom in a society corrupted by political pull,
and watches Dagnian Reardon race to complete the John Gault line before their enemies can stop them.
The title, The Exploitors and the Exploited, inverts the Marxist narrative that capitalist exploit workers.
Rand argues the opposite. It is the looters who exploit the producers, using government force to seize
what they cannot earn.
the equalization of opportunity bill passes.
This legislation forces any business owner who operates in multiple industries to divest from all but one.
Reardon, who owns steel mills and or mines, must sell his mines.
The bill is presented as helping the little guy, giving smaller competitors a chance against industrial giants.
But look at what it actually does.
It strips a productive man of property he built through decades of work,
transferring it to competitors who never demonstrated the ability to create it themselves.
The men who voted for this bill, who knows by what mines,
who knows whose will place them in power, what motive move them, what was their knowledge,
which one of them, unated, could bring a single chunk of ore out of the earth.
This is the inversion of exploitation.
The productive are forced to surrender their creations to the unproductive.
Achievement is punished.
In competence is rewarded.
Wesley Much reveals his true colors.
Rardon had employed much as his Washington lobbyist,
paid him to represent his interests.
But Much has been working with the conspirators all along.
His reward for betrayal,
appointment as assistant coordinator of the Bureau of Economic Planning and National Resources.
Much traded his integrity for power,
and in the new system, that's a profitable trade.
The lesson is clear.
You cannot work within a corrupt system.
Hiring lobbyists to deal with government is futile when the government rewards those who serve the looters,
not those who create value.
Rardon realizes too late that he was funding his own destruction.
Every dollar he paid Much was used against him.
Meanwhile, Dagnian Reardon worked frantically to complete the John Gaunt line.
The railroad through Colorado built with Reardon Metal.
They face opposition from every direction.
The media predicts disaster.
The State Science Institute questions the metal safety.
James Taggart undermines his own sister.
But they press forward, determined to prove that achievement is possible despite every attempt to stop it.
The John Gaunt line becomes more than a railroad.
It becomes a symbol.
A test of whether productive people can still accomplish great things in a world designed to prevent them.
Dagnian names it after the question that haunts the world.
Who is John Gaunt?
Her answer?
We are.
The producers.
The creators.
The people who refuse to give up.
Let's recap what we learned today.
The equalization of opportunity bill forces Reardon to sell his or mines,
rewarding the incompetent at the expense of the productive.
Wesley Moch's betrayal shows that working within the system is futile.
The system rewards those who serve the looters.
The true exploiters are not the industrialists,
but the looters who use government force to seize what they cannot create.
And Dagnian Reardon prepared to answer the question,
who is John Gault with their own achievement?
The John Gault line.
In the next episode, we'll witness the triumphant first run of the John Gault line.
Dagnian Reardon will stake their lives on their own work.
Writing in the engine cab is the train crosses the revolutionary Reardon metal bridge.
See you in the next one.