Using Bitcoin in funds is the most obvious and non-thinking way for a fund,
their investors and their investors' shareholders, to sleepwalk their way to unimaginable wealth.
Despite being declared dead many times by mainstream media,
declared useless by respected economists, and called only useful to money-launders by Larry Fink.
Bitcoin closed 2024 near all-time highs.
Ordinary people who simply held Bitcoin outperformed every hedge fund, mutual fund,
and special purpose fund. If you are a mutual fund manager reading this and your company still
isn't offering Bitcoin, you must wonder what they're doing. What are all of those employees
actually doing all day? There are tens, maybe hundreds of thousands of ordinary people,
most of whom would never pass the hiring process of any investment company,
who have massively outperformed every professional fund manager simply by buying and holding Bitcoin.
Bitcoin's 16-year return history makes it the best performing asset class in history,
despite massive drawdowns along the way.
Professional money managers who ignored it have significant explaining to do.
Research consistently shows that even small allocations to Bitcoin can dramatically improve
portfolio metrics. A traditional 60-40 portfolio with zero Bitcoin might return 8% with a sharp
ratio of 0.53. Add just 1% Bitcoin, and you're looking at over 9% returns with a sharp ratio of
0.60. At 2% allocation, your over 10% returns with a sharp ratio of 0.66. At 5%, you're at 14%
returns with a sharp ratio of 0.80. The improvement in risk-adjusted returns is remarkable for such small
allocations. The volatility increases modest, but the return improvement is substantial.
The traditional concern is that fiduciaries face liability for including Bitcoin and experiencing
drawdowns, but the calculus is shifting, the old view. We can't include Bitcoin because if it
drops 50%, we'll be sued. The new view. If we don't include Bitcoin, and it 10Xs, while our competitors
include it, we'll be sued for not including it. Bitcoin drawdowns are temporary,
historically always recovering to new highs, but missing Bitcoin's appreciation is permanent.
Fiduciaries face greater long-term risk from exclusion than inclusion. Many funds have unintentional
short exposure to Bitcoin through their positions. Banks compete with Bitcoin for the store-of-value
function. Payment processors compete with Bitcoin's payment rails. Fiat currencies are in direct
competition for the monetary premium. Long duration bonds serve the same role as a monetary hedge.
Gold miners are in direct competition as hard money. If your fund holds these assets without
Bitcoin exposure, you may be structurally short Bitcoin, even without intending to be. Target
date funds represent the single largest opportunity for Bitcoin integration. They hold trillions in assets,
even 1% Bitcoin allocation would create massive demand. Young workers have 30 to 40-year horizons,
perfect for Bitcoin's volatility profile. Target date fund investors are passive. They won't panic
sell during drawdowns because they don't watch daily prices. And the structure naturally
rebalances, selling high and buying low over time. These, sedate and forget it funds for retirement
savers could include Bitcoin in their equity allocation with minimal friction. Let's recap what we
learned in this chapter. Ordinary Bitcoin holders outperformed every professional fund. Fund
managers who ignored Bitcoin have explaining to do. Small allocations generate significant alpha.
Even 1% to 2% Bitcoin can meaningfully improve portfolio sharp ratios. Fiduciary risk is shifting.
The greater liability may now be from not including Bitcoin rather than including it. Don't be
unintentionally short Bitcoin. Holdings in banks, payment processors, and bonds may create hidden
short exposure. Target date funds are the biggest opportunity, trillions in assets with long
horizons and passive investors. In the next episode, we'll explore treasury and balance sheet
strategies. How companies can use Bitcoin treasuries beyond just holding for appreciation. See you in
the next one.